# **Akhil Gupta**

Technology Leader/Practitioner ex Lowes ex ThoughtWorks ex Sapient, Yatra Fellow, Tech Entrepreneur - Result Oriented, Hands-On, Versatile Professional



A11-1004 TULIP VIOLET SECTOR 69 GURGAON HARYANA 122101 INDIA (+91) (987) 360-0485 AKHIL@AKHILGUPTA.COM

#### **OVERVIEW**

Has solved numerous business complexities by strategic implementation of technology in a career spanning over 28 years. Has worked in reputed software consulting companies, digital retailers as well as Internet startups in leadership positions. Well-traveled, has global work exposure in American, European and APAC regions. His knowledge of technology, business and people management raises competitiveness through continuous improvement and optimization. Very effective in Internet, product development, technology consulting or software-delivery organizations.

### **EXPERIENCE**

# **Yatra.com (NASDAQ NM YTRA),** Gurgaon, India — Senior Vice President, Technology

NOVEMBER 2021 - PRESENT

Responsible for transforming the travel technology landscape in Yatra.com. Preparing the technology for the future through a series of architectural improvements, standardization, enhancing the re-use and adoption of all the best practices prevalent in the market today through technology accelerators. Additionally responsible for rebuilding a great talent team in the three development centers – Gurgaon, Bangalore and Kochi.

# **Lowe's (NASDAQ NM LOW),** Bangalore, India — Senior Director, Enterprise Architecture

JUNE 2020 - NOVEMBER 2021

Responsible for thought leadership on Enterprise Architecture and design efficiency of high impact technology initiatives of Lowe's which is a Fortune 50, 100 years old Home Improvement retailer in the USA. Primary focus on the Digital technology portfolio of the business with additional technical contributions to various other areas of the enterprise too. Additional ownerships include Canada Digital portfolio, Cloud Center of Excellence and Cloud Steering Committee.

# **ThoughtWorks (NASDAQ NM TWKS),** Gurgaon, India — Principal Technologist

MAY 2018 - JUNE 2020

Responsible for technology leadership in high-value client engagements around Digital Transformation and Digital Platform Strategy. This role

### **RECENT ENGAGEMENTS**

**Lowe's** - Fortune 50 Home Improvement Retailer

**Gucci** - #1 Global Luxury Fashion Brand

AirAsia - Asia's leading low cost airline

**Falabella -** South American Retailer

Axis Bank - 3rd largest private bank in India

**Grainger** - Fortune 500 American industrial supply company

PVR Cinemas - Asia's largest cinema network

Yatra.com - India's leading OTA

### **LANGUAGES**

English, Hindi, German

### **SOCIAL NETWORKING**

LinkedIn linkedin.com/in/akhildelhi

WordPress Thoughtsbyakhil.wordpress

#### **RECOMMENDATIONS**

"He is a natural agile leader

requires key stakeholder management and interactions at CXO levels for adoption of complex technology principals that have been mastered by ThoughtWorks and industry. Requires thought and technology leadership; engagement with both technical and non-technical client leadership; knowledge of product lifecycle; and collaboration with a global business development team.

### RateTag e-Commerce (P) Ltd, New Delhi, India — *Director*, Co-Founder

DECEMBER 2012 - MAY 2018

Author of a 'vertical and business model agnostic', hybrid e-commerce marketplace technology platform. A market-validated product, the platform powers some hot e-Commerce startups. The company also offers ad-hoc technology consulting and implementation services to customers in India, United States and Europe under leadership of Akhil.

# **Yatra.com (NASDAQ NM YTRA),** Gurgaon, India — *Vice President, Technology*

JUL 2007 - DECEMBER 2012

Responsible for strategic initiatives, new projects, market disruptive innovations. Owned complete product and technology portfolio. Incubated new business units, operationalized in a fixed time-frame. Guided the design, planning, execution and maintenance of software development projects, planning and commissioning of data centers, networks, remote offices. Led partner engagements, vendor identification, request for proposals, negotiations and procurement. Led a highly skilled 65 people internal team and 100 people outsourced team

# **Sapient Corporation (NASDAQ NM SAPE),** Gurgaon, India — Senior Manager Technology

SEPTEMBER 2006 - JULY 2007

Guided the design, user interface, and technology integration of projects, interfaced with client's technology and management teams, and gathered information on enterprise-wide trends. The job required leadership and managerial skills to independently manage 30+ people, during multiple phases of the project lifecycle; Experience providing a vision to the total solution, managing a track of work and defining a comprehensive solution leading toward a common vision.

### **Sify (NASDAQ NM SIFY),** Chennai, India — Technical Architect

FEBRUARY 2006 - SEPTEMBER 2006

Managed Consumer Product Development including interfacing with Business Teams to develop functional requirements, Technical Design and Architecture, Software Development, Implementation, Testing and Technology Support for Consumer Businesses – Web Portals, Mobile Applications

capable of understanding all the requirements from a few elements and guiding a team in the design of complex solutions." - Mauro Antelmi, Chief Architect, Gucci

"Akhil demonstrated an amazing blend of an entrepreneurial mindset and a hands-on technology leader a trait that is very rare." -Rajnish Kapur, Managing Partner, IAN Fund

"Akhil is a terrific master of all trades. He can take any problem, jump on it, and come up with a strong solution." - Apul Choudhary, VP, AMEX

"Akhil is a true professional, very focused on his goals, flexible, a very good team worker and keeps his team motivated at all times." -Bhavna Agarwal, CEO, HP Enterprise

"Akhil Gupta, man of many talents. Akhil is very passionate about his work and has very strong technical knowledge. Never says no to anything and always comes up with new ideas and solutions." - Manish Amin, CIO & Co-Founder, Yatra.com

"Akhil Gupta is one of the most versatile and capable professionals I have worked with. He is a true team player, has an eye for detail and his breadth of understanding of software development is amazing." - Puneet Sachdev, Corporate VP, WNS Global Services

"He offers a rare blend of tech

### **Mokshita Technologies,** New Delhi, India — *Software Architect*

APRIL 1998 - JANUARY 2006

Technology lead in various Web Applications Development and System Integration projects for companies in the USA, UK, Australia and India.

# **Asquire Computers (P) Ltd,** New Delhi, India — *System Integration Engineer*

APRIL 1995 - APRIL 1998

Led various System Integration projects for various Indian companies. Work included deployment and management of IT Infrastructure, software integration, ITSM systems

#### **EDUCATION**

# **Board of Technical Education,** New Delhi, India — Diploma in *Computer Engineering – 3 Years*

JUNE 1992 - JULY 1995

First Division with Distinction – Evaluated in United States to 16 Years Bachelor's Degree Program in Computer Science and Engineering in conjunction with Work Experience

# **IEC University,** Himachal Pradesh, India — Bachelor of Computer Applications – 3 Years

AUGUST 2015 - AUGUST 2018

First Division (CGPA 6.76) A Bachelor's Degree program in computer software application design and development

# **Goethe Institut,** Munich, Germany — Advanced Level German Language - 3 *Years*

JUNE 1992 - JULY 1995

B1 Level German Language Certified with 2 years of advanced studies of Business Management conducted in German language (Compliant with Germany's Professional Workers Immigration Requirements)

### Narsee Monjee Institute of Management Studies, Mumbai, India — MBA - 2 Years

FEBRUARY 2022 - JANUARY 2024

Master of Business Administration with specialization in Marketing Management - continuous learning and upskilling goal for 2024

### **MISCELLANEOUS INFORMATION**

| Year Of Birth : 1974            |
|---------------------------------|
| ☐ Nationality : Indian          |
| ☐ Ethnicity: South Asian        |
| Religion: Hindu                 |
| ☐ Travel Capability: 25% to 40% |
| ☐ Disability: None              |
| ☐ Military Veteran Status: None |

depth, commercial acumen, startup experience, domain expertise (in travel and retail) and product thinking. He is unconventional and constructively opinionated, as you might expect for somebody who has successfully founded and sold his own product startup." – Anirvan Lahiri, Co-Worker, ThoughtWorks

"Akhil is an engaging leader with deep knowledge in the areas of Retail and E-commerce." - Prerna Thakur, Co-Worker, ThoughtWorks

More reviews and recommendations on LinkedIn Profile

| Passport : Yes                                     |
|--|
| Internationally Traveled - Yes - USA, Europe, Asia |
| Married: Yes                                       |
| Children: Yes, 2                                   |